So דף יב עמוד א, daf yud bet amud aleph, right near
the bottom. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. It's about eight lines from the
bottom. אמר רבא בר חיננא סבא משמיה דרב, Amar Rava bar Chinana
Sabba mishmei deRav, כל שלא אמר אמת ויציב שחרית ואמת ואמונה ערבית
לא יצא ידי חובתו. Kol shelo amar emet veyatziv shachrit ve’emet ve’emuna
arvit lo yatza yedei chovato. So we've been talking now about the
ברכות brachot that come around the שמע Shema before and after the
שמע. Shema. We discussed the ברכות brachot before of יוצר המאורות Yotzer
HaMeorot and אהבה רבה Ahava Rabba and talked about how יוצר המאורות
Yotzer HaMeorot was more about the morning and similar מעריב ערבים Maariv
Aravim and אהבה רבה Ahava Rabba and אהבת עולם Ahavat Olam were
about more about the שמע Shema and about תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah.
And we even discussed the possibility for יוצר המאורות Yotzer HaMeorot like
to say שמע Shema without יוצר המאורות Yotzer HaMeorot if it's not
yet time fully for the morning, which emphasizes that difference. And now
we're moving into the ברכות brachot at the end. אמת ויציב. Emet
Veyatziv. So he says if you don't say אמת ויציב Emet Veyatziv
שחרית shachris and אמת ואמונה Emet Ve’emuna ערבית arvis לא יצא ידי
חובתו. lo yatza yedei chovaso. So he's not just talking about to
say a ברכה bracha at the end of שמע, Shema, which we
know, but he's talking specifically about the specific language. So the same
way we had a difference of מעריב ערבים Maariv Aravim and יוצר
המאורות Yotzer HaMeorot or which is obvious, or more subtly, אהבה רבה
Ahava Rabba and אהבת עולם, Ahavat Olam, here he says there's also
a difference in the ברכה bracha afterwards. That it's אמת ויציב Emet
Veyatziv in the morning and אמת ואמונה Emet Ve’emuna in the evening.
Why? שנאמר Shenemar להגיד בבוקר חסדך ואמונתך בלילות lehagid baboker chasdecha ve’emunatecha
baleilot to teach your, you know, to talk about your kindness in
the morning and the faith in you at the night. So presumably
again exactly this difference about as sort of parallel to the אהבה
רבה Ahava Rabba and אהבת עולם Ahavat Olam that in the morning
you really have this appreciation of the wonderful beneficence and gifts of
God and the אהבה רבה Ahava Rabba life, the sun, the world,
and the evening it starts evoking more sense of sort of fear,
you know, the darkness and concern about, you know, the night and
waking up the next day, and therefore that's the more אהבת עולם
Ahavat Olam the sense of enduring love and here also the אמת
ואמונה. Emet Ve’emuna. It's not, it's the sense of not of that
it's the faith aspect that's an important part of the night. So
there's a nice little parallel in terms of those two.
And now the גמרא Gemara continues. רש"י Rashi by the way, if
you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says
וברכת ubirchas רש"י Rashi two lines before the line get why, וברכת
אמת ויציב כולה על חסד שעשה עם אבותינו שהוציאנו ממצרים ובקע למו
הים והעבירם. ubirchas Emet Veyatziv kula al chesed she’asa im avoteinu she’tzi’anu
miMitzrayim ve’baka lamo hayam ve’he’eviram.
So רש"י Rashi says it's not just the word יציב, Yatziv, it's
the content of the ברכה. bracha. The אמת ויציב Emet Veyatziv ברכה
bracha in the morning is all about the נסים nissim or all
about the חסד chesed and the beneficence that God has given us.
וברכת אמת ואמונה מדבר בה אף
על העתידות. ubirchas Emet Ve’emuna medaber ba af al ha’atidot. And אמת
ואמונה Emet Ve’emuna is about, look, a hope for the future. מצפים
שיקיים לנו הבטחתו ואמונתו לגאלנו מיד מלכים Metzapim sheyikayem lanu havtachato ve’emunato
lega’alenu miyad melachim and so on.
And I think again it's not just about praise for the past
and hope for the future but again, well it is, but it's
reflected also by just morning evening experiential difference which is also the
אהבה רבה Ahava Rabba and אהבת עולם. Ahavat Olam. Okay and now
the גמרא Gemara continues. ואמר רבא בר בר חנה אמר בר חיננא
סבא משמיה דרב Ve’amar Rava bar Bar Chana Amar Bar Chinana Sabba
mishmei deRav המתפלל כשהוא כורע כורע בברוך. hamitpallel kshehu kore’a kore’a bebaruch.
If somebody דאוונס davens when they are bending down then they should
bend down at ברוך. Baruch.
וכשהוא זוקף זוקף בשם. ukshehu zokef zokef beshem. I'm sorry, I put
the comma in the wrong place. המתפלל, Hamitpallel, when one דאוונס, davens,
כשהוא כורע כורע בברוך, kshehu kore’a kore’a bebaruch, you, when you do
the bowing, you bow at ברוך. Baruch. וכשהוא זוקף ukshehu zokef and
when you do the standing up, זוקף בשם, zokef beshem, you do
it when you say שם השם. Shem Hashem. So it's ברוך אתה,
Baruch Ata, you bend your knees, you know, at the ברוך Baruch
and then you're bowed down at the אתה. Ata. Then when you
say God's name, you're bowing up as it were, you're becoming erect
at the name of God.
אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel מאי טעמא דרב? mai ta’ama deRav? What's the
reasoning of this? דכתיב Dechtiv the פסוק pasuk says
השם זוקף כפופים, Hashem zokef kefufim, God causes those that are bent
to be standing up, to be upright. So therefore the name of
God makes us from that bent state to the to the upright
state. So the גמרא Gemara says מתיבי, metivei, I'll ask you on
this. מפני שמי נחת הוא, Mipnei shemi nichat hu, because of my
name he is sort of, you know, humbled. So you see God's
name causes that sense of being lowly, of humility and not of
standing up. So the גמרא Gemara says מי כתיב בשמי? michativ bishmi?
With the expression, with the articulation of my, saying of
my name? מפני שמי כתיב, Mipnei shemi ktiv,
because of my name. So my name causes that sense of humility
but in the utterance of God's name, that actually causes us to
rise. And again, this is this dialectic and tension that I think
we've been seeing before, that praying to God on the one hand
has to imbue us with a tremendous sense of awe and humility
and our smallness and at the other hand we're reaching. Reaching out
to God, which is that sense of connection. So before we had,
you stand in a low place but you stand with your feet
combined like an angel. So both that sense of where our striving
for connection and that sense of our humility. So here too, you
have the bowing down, you know, that sense that we're nothing, we're
on the ground, you know, in the presence of God, but then
also the saying of God's name, the reaching out to connect is
also what rises us up. So I think that's a beautiful play
in terms of the sort of competing themes that are going on
here. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה שמואל לחייא בר רב.
Amar leh Shmuel leChiya bar Rav. So שמואל Shmuel says to חייא
בר רב, Chiya bar Rav, בר אוריין, Bar Oryan,
which could mean son of a lion or could mean a תלמיד
חכם Talmid Chacham like אורייתא Oraita תורה. Torah. תא אימא לך מילתא
מעלייתא דאמר אבוך. Ta ema lach milta maalyata de'amar avuch.
Go tell us something nice that your father said. תא אימא לך,
Ta ema lach, come
let me tell you. Boy, okay, let me tell you something beautiful
that your father said. הכי אמר אבוך, Hachi amar avuch, here's what
your father said. כשהוא כורע, כורע בברוך וכשהוא זוקף, זוקף בשם. Keshehu
koreiah, koreiah be'Baruch, ucheshehu zokef, zokef beShem. Exactly what we said before.
So here he is reporting it to שמואל Shmuel is reporting it
to חייא בר רב Chiya bar Rav in the name of his
father like we saw before that this was taught in the name
of רב. Rav. Turning to page דף י"ב עמוד ב', Daf Yud
Bet Amud Bet, רב ששת כי כרע, כרע כחיזרא. Rav Sheshet ki
kara, kara kachizra. When רב ששת Rav Sheshet bowed down, he would
bow down like a rod. Like if you threw a rod to
the ground, you know, it would be like falling down immediately, you
know, in one shot
without hesitation.
וכי זקיף, זקיף כחיויא. Vechi zakif, zakif kachivya. And when he would
rise up,
he would rise up like a snake. You know, like the way
a snake sort of slowly rises, you know, like the snake charmer
or whatever as they rise off the ground from their head, very
slow and gradual. So again, sort of emphasizing,
you know, רש"י Rashi says that the bowing down should not look
like a משא massa like you're quick to get up. So emphasizing,
you know, the immediate sense of your sense of awe in coming
before God and the reaction is immediate and then sort of gaining
the strength to rise up, which is a slow process. So again,
playing with that tension but giving the emphasis towards that sense of
awe that has to sort of, you know, the weight has to
be put on that. ואמר רבה בר חיננא סבא משמיה דרב. Ve'amar
Rabbah bar Chinana Sava mishmei deRav. And now another teaching from the
same
tradition, רבה בר חיננא Rabbah bar Chinana in the name of רב.
Rav. כל השנה כולה. Kol hashanah kulah. Now this is not it's
related to דאוונען davening but not the immediate issues we're talking about,
but it is the same
אמורא. Amora. כל השנה כולה אדם מתפלל האל הקדוש. Kol hashanah kulah
adam mitpallel Ha'El HaKadosh. The whole year when you say the first
the third ברכה Bracha of שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, you say האל
הקדוש. Ha'El HaKadosh. And you say מלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט Melech Ohev
Tzedakah uMishpat when you say the ברכה Bracha of משפט mishpat in
the middle, it's מלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט. Melech Ohev Tzedakah uMishpat. That's
our נוסח nusach of course. חוץ מעשרה ימים שבין ראש השנה ליום
הכיפורים. Chutz me'Asarah Yamim shebein Rosh Hashanah leYom Kippur. Except for the
עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. This is technically inaccurate. There are
not ten days between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. There's only seven days. But it means the ten days encompassing
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the עשרת ימי
תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. There we say, what do you say there?
שמתפלל המלך הקדוש והמלך המשפט. Shemitpallel HaMelech HaKadosh veHaMelech HaMishpat. There the
sense of God's מלכות Malchut dominates. And therefore you say not האל
הקדוש Ha'El HaKadosh but המלך הקדוש. HaMelech HaKadosh. And you don't say
and you don't say מלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט, Melech Ohev Tzedakah uMishpat,
but God embodies משפט. mishpat. There the shift is המלך. HaMelech. המלך
HaMelech was always part of that ברכה, Bracha, but it's המלך המשפט.
HaMelech HaMishpat. That that is so much the emphasis of משפט mishpat
as, you know, the identity of God at at that time. So
both מלך Melech is being emphasized and משפט. mishpat.
By the way, I should mention that המלך הקדוש HaMelech HaKadosh is
really what we say on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. That there doesn't seem to have been a debate that
that's the נוסח nusach of the ברכה Bracha on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, המלך הקדוש. HaMelech HaKadosh. But the
question is, do you extend that ברכה Bracha into the עשרת ימי
תשובה Aseret Yemei Teshuvah and then you also pattern similarly after it
מלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט המלך המשפט. Melech Ohev Tzedakah uMishpat, HaMelech HaMishpat.
So he said yes, and that's what you have even in the
עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. רבי אליעזר אומר אפילו אמר האל
הקדוש יצא. Rabbi Eliezer omer, afilu amar Ha'El HaKadosh yatza. Maybe ideally
you should do that, but you know what, בדיעבד bedi'avad you're יוצא
yotzei even if you say האל הקדוש. Ha'El HaKadosh. שנאמר ויגבה ה'
צבאות במשפט והאל הקדוש נקדש בצדקה. Shene'emar: Vayigbah Hashem Tzeva'ot bamishpat, veha'El
HaKadosh nikdash bitzedakah. So the glory of God is lifted up in
judgment and the Holy God is sanctified in righteousness. אימתי ויגבה ה'
צבאות במשפט? Eimatai Vayigbah Hashem Tzeva'ot bamishpat? When is God sort of,
you know, the focus on justice? אלו עשרה ימים שבין ראש השנה
ליום הכיפורים. Elu asarah yamim shebeRosh Hashanah leYom Kippur. This is the
עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. And even during that time when
the emphasis is God as judge, וקאמר האל הקדוש. veka'amar Ha'El HaKadosh.
And nevertheless the end of the פסוק pasuk is האל הקדוש. Ha'El
HaKadosh. So you see האל הקדוש Ha'El HaKadosh is acceptable during that
time. And presumably if האל הקדוש Ha'El HaKadosh is acceptable, מלך אוהב
צדקה ומשפט Melech Ohev Tzedakah uMishpat is also acceptable. מאי הוה לה?
Mai havah lah? What was the upshot of this? אמר רב יוסף
האל הקדוש ומלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט. Amar Rav Yosef, Ha'El HaKadosh uMelech
Ohev Tzedakah uMishpat. רב יוסף Rav Yosef says you keep the normal
נוסח, nusach, presumably not even בדיעבד, bedi'avad, even if you. לכתחילה, lechatchila,
if you say המלך הקדוש, Hamelech Hakadosh, you say it on ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, not on עשרת ימי
תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. רבה אמר, Rabbah amar, המלך הקדוש והמלך המשפט.
Hamelech Hakadosh vehamelech hamishpat. No, you change the גרסא girsa to what
we to המלך הקדוש המלך המשפט Hamelech Hakadosh Hamelech Hamishpat והלכתא כרבה
vehilchata kerabbah and we rule like Rabbah as we know that is
our פסק. psak. Interestingly, take a quick look at תוספות, Tosafot, הלכתא
כוותיה דרבה. hilchata kevasei derabbah. תוספות Tosafot says וצריך לחתום המלך הקדוש
המלך המשפט ואם לא אמר מחזירין אותו, vetzarich lachtom Hamelech Hakadosh Hamelech
Hamishpat ve'im lo amar machzirin oto, so it's merely if you made
a mistake you have to go back. שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei doesn't
count.
And then it says וכן זכרנו ומי כמוך וכתוב לחיים ובספר חיים
מחזירין אותו אם לא אמר. vechen Zachrenu u'mi chamocha u'chtov l'chayim u'vesefer
chayim machzirin oto im lo amar. So all these additions זכרנו ומי
כמוך, Zachrenu u'mi chamocha, all these things which as we know were
added by the גאונים, Geonim, תוספות Tosafot first says once they're added
they become part of the נוסח nusach and if you don't say
it you have to go back. Then in the end תוספות Tosafot
says if you're looking near the bottom by the asterisk ורבינו תם
ve'Rabbeinu Tam or anyway whoever it is, רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, anyway
כותב kotev דאין מחזירין אותם מכל אותן הדברים דלא פסיק בש"ס בפירוש.
d'ein machzirin otam mikol otan hadevarim d'lo pasik be'Shas befeirush. Maybe ראיה
לדבר. re'ayah ladavar. These things were added later by the גאונים Geonim
and therefore if you don't say them you don't go back and
that is how we פוסק. pasken. You go back for המלך הקדוש
Hamelech Hakadosh and המלך המשפט Hamelech Hamishpat but not for the זכרנוס
Zachrenus and וכתבנו u'chtavenu and so on which was added later.
Okay, so now we have three teachings of this רבה בר חיננא
Rabbah bar Chinena in the name of רב. Rav. One which spoke
which started us which was אמת ויציב אמת ואמונה, Emet V'yatziv Emet
V'emunah, the ברכה bracha after שמע. Shema. And now two הלכות halachos
about שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, bowing down and מלך צדקה מלך המשפט.
Melech Tzedakah Melech Hamishpat. ואמר רבה בר חיננא סבא משמיה דרב, v'amar
Rabbah bar Chinena Sava mishmei d'Rav, and now again רבה בר חיננא
Rabbah bar Chinena in the name of רב Rav yet another thing:
כל שאפשר לו לבקש רחמים על חבירו ואינו מבקש נקרא חוטא. kol
she'efshar lo levakesh rachamim al chaveiro ve'eino mevakesh nikra chotei. Again in
the realm of דאוונינג davening but not about the נוסח, nusach, but
about the attitude towards דאוונינג. davening. If you can pray for your
friend, you know that somebody you know needs your prayers, needs רחמים,
rachamim, needs some type of divine aid and you don't pray for
that person, you're a sinner. שנאמר, shene'emar,
the פסוק pasuk says גם אנכי חלילה לי מחטוא לה' מחדול להתפלל
בעדכם. gam anochi chalila li me'chato la'Hashem mechadol l'hitpalel beadchem. As for
me, God forbid for me like you know
that to sin against God מחדול להתפלל בעדכם mechadol l'hitpalel beadchem that
I should hold back from praying for your sake. So you see
that it would be a sin not to pray for somebody's sake.
And it seems like the point here is, you know, it's interesting
because I would say a couple of things. Number one is that,
in general people do statutory prayer, the things that's obligated. That doesn't
really speak so much towards a sense of real faith in how
God operates in the world. I mean it's that is the content
of it, but you do it because you have to. When you're
responding to a
situation and you pray because something's actually happening, that shows like a
real I think a deeper belief in the fact that the role
that God can play in the world. If that were just the
only point, then it wouldn't just be about חבירו, chaveiro, it would
be even about yourself. You know, that if you're not praying in
response to something happening to you, that might show like a certain
lack of faith. The חבירו chaveiro aspect obviously is adding another component.
It's adding the basic sense about caring about your friend. You know,
so if you A, if you have this faith that prayer helps
and God is involved in the world and B, if your friend
needs it and you're not doing it, then you're a sinner because
you are abandoning your friend in this way. So that really gives
this whole power to the efficacy of prayer and how it's something
we do not just because we have to, but we do it's
a way of helping people and that sense of responsibility towards that.
And then the גמרא Gemara continues and says אמר רבא אם תלמיד
חכם הוא, amar Rava im talmid chacham hu, and if the person
who needs your prayers is a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, צריך שיחלה
עצמו עליו. tzarich sheyichleh atzmo alav. It's not just enough to pray,
you have to even like make yourself sick over the person, presumably
because you're so much involved in your prayer. You really have to
go the extra mile. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אילימא משום דכתיב, eilima
mishum dechtiv, why do we know this? Is it because the פסוק
pasuk says ואין חולה מכם עלי וגולה את אזני? ve'ein choleh mikem
alay vegoleh et ozni? Nobody this was Saul complaining about being informed
about דוד. David. Nobody, the way the one of the English translations
this is nobody cares about me, is concerned about me, or is
revealing to my ear what's going on. But the גמרא's Gemara reading
it literally, חולה, choleh, nobody's making you're not getting making yourself sick
over me. You know? So it's really like the you know it's
like a classic Jewish mother. You know you know you love somebody
when you get sick over them. So anyway, דילמא מלך שאני, dilma
melech shani, maybe it's just for the king you should make yourself
sick, not for just a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So גמרא Gemara
says אלא מהכא ela me'hacha from here: ואני בחלותם לבושי v'ani bechalotam
levushi and I in their illness, you know, I dressed in the
sackcloth and so on. So this is David talking about how he
afflicted himself. Now again the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is
that he afflicted himself when others became ill. But we're reading it
presumably that he made him self ill for their sake. So that's
taking it even beyond just obviously the issue of prayer. ואמר רבי
חנינא בר אבא משמיה דרב, ve'amar Rabbi Chinana bar Abba mishmeih deRav,
again Rabbi חנינא בר אבא Chinana bar Abba משמיה דרב, mishmeih deRav,
כל עושה דבר עבירה ומתבייש בו. kol ose devar aveirah umisbayes bo.
Now we're shifting from prayer to different areas. Although of course there
is a very common theme here, you know he's not talking to
us about הלכות halachos about, you know, גרמי. garmi. I mean, it's
very much about these sort of religious, ethical types of teachings. That
anybody who does a, who sins and is embarrassed by it, is
sort of, you know, is shamed by what he has done, מוחלין
לו על כל עוונותיו, mochlin lo al kol avonosav, all of his
sins are forgiven. This connects I probably to the theme we talked
earlier, you know, where the גמרא Gemara says like, if you can,
if you internalize a message, it's better than being like, you know,
getting a hundred lashes. That when, if you actually feel the shame
and feel the embarrassment and you internalize that, that could have a
profound transformative experience of your personality and of your future actions. And
that's what I think the idea of מוחלין לו על כל עוונותיו
mochlin lo al kol avonosav is. Not just like, oh you're suffering
and that causes atonement, but it's actually that the feeling of the
shame hopefully can really lead to a transformative experience.
שנאמר, shenemar, as it says, למען תזכרי ובושת ולא יהיה לך
עוד פתחון פה מפני כלימתך בכפרי לך לכל אשר עשית נאום השם.
lema'an tizkeri uvoshat velo yihyeh lach od pischon peh mipnei kelimasech bechapperi
lach lechol asher asis neum Hashem. In order that you should remember
and be embarrassed and you will no longer have any response because
of your shame when I atone for you for all that you
have done, says God, נאום השם אלוקים. neum Hashem Elokim. So there
you see the way it's reading it is because you have the
shame and embarrassment, therefore I will atone for you. So the גמרא
Gemara says דלמא ציבור שאני? dilma tzibbur shani? Maybe that was when
the entire ציבור, tzibbur, all of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael was shamed,
which is the sort of story there that we'll be shown up
for our sins. Maybe that's different, that's of a different, you know,
character. אלא מהכא, ela meihacha, how about an individual? From the following
פסוק. pasuk. ויאמר שמואל אל שאול, vayomer Shmuel el Shaul, שמואל Shmuel
says to שאול, Shaul, when שאול Shaul raised up שמואל Shmuel from
the dead, right his spirit. למה הרגזתני להעלות אותי, lamah hirgaztani leha'alos
osi, why did you disturb me to raise me up? ויאמר שאול
vayomer Shaul and שאול Shaul said,
צר לי מאד ופלשתים נלחמים בי והאלהים סר מעלי ולא ענני עוד
גם ביד הנביאים גם בחלומות
ואקראה לך להודיעני מה אעשה. tzar li me'od ufelishtim nilchamim bi veha'elohim
sar me'alai velo anani od gam beyad hanevi'im gam bachalomos va'ekre'ah lecha
lehodi'eni mah e'eseh. Therefore I had to raise your spirit up so
you could tell me how I should act. So that's what he
said. And now the גמרא Gemara comments on this, ואילו אורים ותומים
לא קאמר, ve'ilu urim vesummim lo ka'amar, but he didn't say, I
tried the אורים ותומים Urim VeSummim and I didn't get an answer
from the אורים ותומים. Urim VeSummim. Why didn't he say that? משום
דקטלי לנוב עיר הכהנים, mishum dekatlei leNov ir hakohanim, because there was
nobody to ask the אורים ותומים Urim VeSummim about the אורים ותומים
Urim VeSummim or because he had wiped out the entire city of
כהנים. Kohanim. So there was no, you know, so it was very
hard to go ask the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol the אורים ותומים
Urim VeSummim after having wiped out that entire city. So the גמרא
Gemara understands that because he didn't mention it, that shows that he
was embarrassed about that and embarrassed about what he had done to
wipe out the entire city. And therefore he was avoiding saying it.
Now as far as you and me are concerned, you know, not
talking about something that you did wrong doesn't necessarily, you know, reflect
the greatest degree of shame or embarrassment, but nevertheless for the גמרא
Gemara that's significant enough to say that look, he actually had a
sense of the wrongness of his deed. And therefore ומניין דאחלו ליה
מן שמיא, uminnayin de'achalu leh min shamaya, so how do we prove
our point that as a result of that he was forgiven? שנאמר
shenemar because the פסוק pasuk says ומחר אתה
ובניך עמי. umachar attah uvanaycha immi. And שמואל Shmuel said to שאול
Shaul tomorrow you and your children will be with me because they
were going to die in that war. So what does that prove?
It just means they'll die. No. ואמר רבי יוחנן עמי במחיצתי, ve'amar
Rabbi Yochanan immi bimchitzasi, you will be in my, in my, you
know, in my מחיצה, mechitza, in my, in my special region in
the world to come. So therefore you will have merit to the
world to come and why will that be? Because since you were
embarrassed and you didn't mention this thing that you had done wrong,
you, all of your sins will be forgiven. So it's a pretty
low level of embarrassment I would say that's being asked of us.
ורבנן אמרי מהכא verabbanan amri meihacha and the Rabbis say from the
following פסוק. pasuk. והוקענום לה' בגבעת שאול בחיר ה'. vehoka'anum l'Hashem begivas
Shaul bechir Hashem. Right, this is when, you know, דוד David asks
the גבעונים Givonim who's, you know, about how to atone for the
sins of שאול Shaul and so on and they said take the
sons of שאול Shaul and sort of and put, you know, and
basically spear them and rise them up on, you know, in front
of God, you know, in the sun in the presence of God.
So what does that prove? Because it says בחיר ה'. bechir Hashem.
Here the גבעונים Givonim are talking about the way שאול Shaul had
sinned against them and they're calling, and what does it mean to
call him the chosen of God? So the גמרא Gemara says it's
not the גבעונים Givonim who are saying it, it's the narrator who's
saying בחיר ה'. bechir Hashem. יצאה בת קול ואמרה. yatzah bas kol
ve'amarah. The גבעונים Givonim said, you know, sort of do this to
the sons of שאול, Shaul, and a heavenly voice said, oh שאול,
Shaul, he's בחיר השם. Bechir Hashem. So why is שאול Shaul בחיר
השם? Bechir Hashem? Must be because he was embarrassed and he didn't
mention the story of נוב עיר כהנים. Nov Ir Kohanim. Okay, so
that was pretty interesting, I mean, you know, from the degree of
shame you would think would be required to make such a statement
to what we see actually occurred by שאול. Shaul. Now the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר רבי אבא בר זוטרא אמר רב יהודה בר זבידה.
Amar Rabbi Abba bar Zutra Amar Rav Yehuda bar Zvida. Now that's
the end of אגדתא, Aggadata, of our digression, or not אגדתא, Aggadata,
but whatever, of our digression away from that statement about the נצח
Nitzach of אמת ואמונה Emes Ve'emuna and אמת ויציב. Emes VeYatziv. And
now we go back to talking about the liturgy around שמע. Shema.
So let's take a look.
Is there a question? No?
If somebody could put it on mute please unless you have a
question. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבי
אבא בר זוטראתי אמר רבי יהודה בר זבידה בקשו לקבוע פרשת בלק
בקריאת שמע. Amar Rabbi Abba bar Zutrati Amar Rabbi Yehuda bar Zvida
bikshu likvoa parshas Balak bekrias Shema. They wanted part of קריאת שמע
Krias Shema to include the פרשה parsha of בלק. Balak. That's pretty
fascinating. Which aspect of it? There's a lot of that פרשה. parsha.
Anyway, מפני מה לא קבעוה? mipnei ma lo kva'uha? Why didn't they
do it? משום טורח ציבור. mishum torach tzibur. Because maybe they wanted
to include all of the beautiful prophecies, not clear how much of
that they wanted to include. But anyway, it would have been super
long. So therefore they didn't include it. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why did they want to include it? What
was powerful about it?
אילמא משום דכתיב בה
Ilima mishum
de'ksiv ba אל מוציאם ממצרים.
El motzi'am miMitzrayim.
Maybe it's because it says, you know, the God that brought them
out of Egypt. So maybe it was a substitute for the פרשה
parsha of ציצית, Tzitzis, which is about יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. So
that's really the major function of the פרשה parsha of ציצית Tzitzis
is יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. We do two מצוות mitzvos in שמע.
Shema. We do the מצווה mitzvah of קריאת שמע, Krias Shema, and
the third פרשה parsha is a separate מצווה mitzvah of remembering יציאת
מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. So it wouldn't have to be the ציצית. Tzitzis.
Maybe the remembering of יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim could have been done
by reading the פרשה parsha of בלק Balak and reading the פסוק
pasuk of אל מוציאם ממצרים. El motzi'am miMitzrayim.
So that says it's actually they wanted to do that and they
would have done it had it not been that long. So then
the גמרא Gemara continues and says the following. It says, אלא, ella,
wait a minute, לימא פרשת ריבית ופרשת משקלות. leima parshas ribbis uparshas
mishkalos. So it talks about God taking us out of Egypt in
a lot of places. In one when it says don't do, you
know, about the prohibition of ריבית ribbis or about just weights, you
know, it says about God having taken us out of Egypt. דכתיב
בהן יציאת מצרים. De'ksiv ban Yetzias Mitzrayim. So that it couldn't have
been that alone.
אלא אמר רבי יוסי בר אבין משום דכתיב בה האי קרא Ella
Amar Rabbi Yose bar Avin mishum de'ksiv ba hai kra כרע שכב
כארי וכלביא מי יקימנו kara shachav ke'ari u'che'lavia mi yekimenu that, you
know, we בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael crouched down like a lion and
like a, and like again, like a whelp, who will rise us
up? So רש"י Rashi says that exactly parallels קריאת שמע, Krias Shema,
lying down and rising up. So if we're looking for a way
to include יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim in קריאת שמע, Krias Shema, why
not do it through פרשת בלק parshas Balak that echoes the theme
of קריאת שמע? Krias Shema? So the גמרא Gemara says, ולימא האי
פסוקא ותו לא? uleima hai pasuka vetulo? So fine, so don't say
the whole thing. Say that פסוק pasuk and say אל מוציאם ממצרים
El motzi'am miMitzrayim and then we'll be done. So you don't need
טורח ציבור, torach tzibur, you'll just do the key components. So the
גמרא Gemara says, גמירי, gemiri, no, we have a tradition, כל פרשה
דפסקיה משה רבינו פסקינן. kol parsha de'paska Moshe Rabbeinu paski'nan. Any פרשה
parsha that משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu divided, we can divide. דלא פסקיה
משה רבינו לא פסקינן. delo paska Moshe Rabbeinu lo paski'nan. If משה
Moshe didn't divide it, we can't divide it. So we can't just
do selections from בלק. Balak. It's either all of it or none
of it. Now I should say by the way that sometimes the
line is כל פסוק דלא פסקיה משה לא פסקינן. kol pasuk delo
paska Moshe lo paski'nan. And here it's כל פרשה דלא פסקיה משה.
kol parsha delo paska Moshe. And the difference seems to be that
the כל פסוק, kol pasuk, we don't divide a פסוק pasuk when
we're even like when we're talking, you should say a whole פסוק.
pasuk. Which is by the way when the גמרא Gemara quotes a
part of a פסוק, pasuk, it always says וגומר ve'gomer as opposed
to וכולו. ve'chulu. I don't know if people are aware of the
difference. Both וכולו ve'chulu and וגומר ve'gomer mean etcetera, dot dot dot.
But וכולו ve'chulu is used when it's not quoting a פסוק. pasuk.
וגומר ve'gomer is used when it's quoting a פסוק pasuk because the
idea when you quote a פסוק pasuk is you have to end
it, you have to complete it, וגומר. ve'gomer. So say the whole
פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, there the issue is more about, is more about
you know that even as an individual you know when you're talking
you're not supposed to say half of a פסוק. pasuk. Although there
is interesting תשובה teshuvah of רב עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef where
he actually says there's no problem doing it and especially like if
you're learning גמרא Gemara and so on you don't have to end
the פסוק. pasuk. But anyway, here when we don't divide a פרשה,
parsha, that's more in terms of using it as a part of
the liturgy. That you know you can obviously quote a פסוק pasuk
without quoting the whole פרשה. parsha. But to make something part of
the liturgy we're not going to do a half of a פרשה.
parsha. So that's why we do not do בלק. Balak. So now
the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, so פרשת ציצית מפני מה קבעוה? parshas
Tzitzis mipnei ma kva'uha?
Is there a question?
No?
Ah yes, we say רש"י וכולו Rashi ve'chulu and that's just one
verse
in... When we
say מה טובו Ma Tovu every day and that's one point.
Yeah, that's an interesting point. Yeah, but you know מה טובו Ma
Tovu is again, that's not like the official you know rabbinic liturgy.
You know, there's no הלכה, halacha, you know, they didn't require us,
there's no הלכה halacha about it, it's מנהג minhag really, saying מה
טובו. Ma Tovu. But you're right, you know, it does sort of
draw the line, what is considered—I mean, we say a lot of
פסוקים psukim and you know, there's one part by the way in
the פסוקי דזמרה Psukei D'zimra which is just a collection of פסוקים
psukim from all over the place, you know, the part that we
say in the middle before—between ברוך שאמר Baruch She'amar and—and אשרי. Ashrei.
So you're right, it does raise questions like what's considered like official
liturgy that has this requirement and what's not. So, you know, here
the real part the חז"ל Chazal emphasize as the official liturgy was
שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, שמע, Shema, וברכות קריאת שמע. u'birchot kriat Shema.
You know,
פסוקי דזמרה Psukei D'zimra even—even פסוקי דזמרה Psukei D'zimra is much more
fluid and whatever. So those are the עיקר ikar sort of liturgy
here of חז"ל, Chazal, but it's a good question. I mean, we're
not really consistent about these rules, I have to tell you, about
the כל פרשת kol parshat and the כל פסוק. kol pasuk. Okay,
so now let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues. It says, so
okay, so we know we want to say, do this other מצוה
mitzvah of זכירת יציאת מצרים. zecher yetziat Mitzrayim. And but why pick
ציצית? Tzitzit? You could have picked a lot of things. So now
we're going to talk about that.
So ופרשת ציצית מפני מה קבעוה? u'parshat Tzitzit mipnei ma kavua? So
why did they pick
ציצית? Tzitzit? אמר רב יהודה בר חביבא מפני שיש בה חמשה דברים,
Amar Rav Yehuda bar Chaviva mipnei she'yesh ba chamisha devarim, because it
has not just יציאת מצרים yetziat Mitzrayim but it has five things.
What does it have? מצות ציצית, mitzvot Tzitzit, which is בעצם b'etzem
מצוה. mitzvah. יציאת מצרים, yetziat Mitzrayim, עול מצוות, ol mitzvot, it also
has the sense of the yoke of מצוות, mitzvot, ועשיתם את כל
מצותי, ve'asitem et kol mitzvotai, which certainly parallels the theme of the
earlier פרשות parshiyot of שמע, Shema, of doing the מצוות. mitzvot. ודעת
מינים, v'da'at minim,
knowledge of heresy. What does that mean? והרהור עבירה, v'hirhur aveira, sinful
thoughts. These are bad things, not good things. והרהור עבודה זרה, v'hirhur
avoda zara, and thoughts of idolatry. What the heck does that mean?
So let's take a look. בשלמא הני תלת מפורשן, Bishlama hani telat
meforashan, the first three we get. עול מצוות דכתיב וראיתם אתו וזכרתם
את כל מצות ה', ol mitzvot de'chtiv u're'item oto u'zechartem et kol
mitzvot Hashem, the עול מצוות ol mitzvot because it says, you know,
you see them and remember the מצוות. mitzvot. ציצית דכתיב ועשו להם
ציצית, Tzitzit de'chtiv ve'asu lahem Tzitzit, okay, ציצית Tzitzit is obvious. ויציאת
מצרים דכתיב אשר הוצאתי אתכם. v'yetziat Mitzrayim de'chtiv asher hotzeti etchem.
The first three we get, okay, and of course as we said,
the benefit of the עול מצוות ol mitzvot besides that it's intrinsically
beneficial ties into the theme of שמע. Shema. But אלא דעת מינים
והרהור עבירה והרהור עבודה זרה מנלן, ela da'at minim v'hirhur aveira v'hirhur
avoda zara menalan, how about these last things? So the גמרא Gemara
says there's a problem if you counted there's six not five, so
some on the side switch the gears so to speak. Anyway, where
do you get them? דתניא, De'tanya,
אחרי לבבכם, acharei levavchem, that you look at the ציצית Tzitzit and
you do not stray after your hearts, זו מינות. zu minut. That's
heresy. Heart sometimes for us is about emotion but heart also can
refer to you know intellect and thought, at least you know in
the sort of at the—in חז"ל Chazal and in the—you know in
their metaphors. So therefore don't stray after your hearts means don't be
misled by you know heretical thought, don't let your intellect lead—lead you
astray from the true faith.
וכן
הוא אומר אמר נבל בלבו אין אלהים, V'chen hu omer amar naval
be'libo ein Elokim, the degenerate one says in his heart there is
no God. So that's a heretical thought and that's בלבו, be'libo, in
your heart. So the ציצית Tzitzit keep you on—keep you focused you
know remembering what you're supposed to be thinking and believing. ואחרי עיניכם,
v'acharei eineichem, don't stray after your eyes, זה הרהור עבירה, zeh hirhur
aveira, that is about sexual sin, שנאמר ויאמר שמשון אל אביו אותה
קח לי כי היא ישרה בעיני. she'ne'emar vayomer Shimshon el aviv otah
kach li ki hi yashra b'einai. Shimshon says to his father, I
want that woman that I found amongst the Pelishtim, she is fit
in my eyes, and there it's בעיני, b'einai, found you know so
seeing a woman, a man seeing a woman and desiring her is
very much emphasis about the visual. So after your eyes is the
sense of being led
again away—about sexual sin. אשר אתם זנים, asher atem zonim, that you
fornicate, which sounds like to be sexual sins, זה הרהור עבודה זרה,
zeh hirhur avoda zara, no that is actually talking about thinking about
idolatry, שנאמר וכן הוא אומר ויזנו אחרי הבעלים, she'ne'emar v'chen hu omer
vayiznu acharei ha'be'alim, and they fornicated after the בעלים, Ba'alim, after the
false God because very often the metaphor is בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
and God is like a marriage and when we worship false gods
we are committing adultery, we are fornicating and so on. So that
is that it has all those three elements. Now of course the
point to point out here is not just that these are intrinsically
important and why not it's a great packed פרשה parsha and it
has יציאת מצרים, yetziat Mitzrayim, it has all these things, let's say
it. But also I would—I would argue that these things also pick
up the theme of שמע. Shema. Not just the מצוות mitzvot but
the idea of מינות minut and עבודה זרה, avoda zara, ה' אלקינו
ה' אחד, Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad, you know that's about accepting God
and the true faith and so on and you know the one
about לא תתורו lo taturu about—about the הרהור עבירה, hirhur aveira, again
that sort of still fits within that. general theme of doing the
מצוות. mitzvos. So part of the פרשה parsha of שמע Shema is
you learn תורה Torah and you do the מצוות, mitzvos, and the
basic emphasis of ציצית Tzitzis is you look at the ציצית tzitsis
and you remember to do the right things and to do the
מצוות mitzvos and not to go after your eyes. So there definitely
is an echoing of the theme and in addition getting the מצוה
mitzvah of יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. And that perfectly leads us in
to the last משנה mishna of the פרק. perek. מזכירין יציאת מצרים
בלילות. Mazkirin Yetzias Mitzrayim baleilos. You mention the Exodus of Egypt at
night, meaning that you mention which means in this context not like
we think when we read in the הגדה Haggadah that we're supposed
to do מגיד maggid פסח Pesach night. This is very much about
the שמע Shema and that you do the מצוה mitzvah of יציאת
מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. We know the שמע Shema is day and night.
There's also a מצוה mitzvah of remembering the Egypt the יציאת מצרים
Yetzias Mitzrayim the Exodus daily. And that's why we say ציצית tzitsis
as we just said. Do we say ציצית tzitsis at night? That's
the question. Maybe it's only to say it once a day. Is
there a מצוה mitzvah to also remember יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim at
night and do we say ציצית? tzitsis? And the משנה mishna says
we do. אמר רבי אלעזר בן עזריה הרי אני כבן שבעים שנה.
Amar Rabbi Elazar Ben Azarya Hareni keven shivim shana. I am like
I was seventy years old. He was younger, but he prayed that
he would look older. You know the story. ולא זכיתי שתאמר יציאת
מצרים בלילות. Velo zachisi shetei'amer Yetzias Mitzrayim baleilos. I never merited understanding
how we could prove or that we should say the Exodus at
night, that that was a מצוה mitzvah as well. עד שדרשה בן
זומא Ad shedrasha Ben Zoma until בן זומא Ben Zoma came and
explained the פסוק pasuk we learn it out from, which is what?
שנאמר למען תזכור את יום צאתך מארץ מצרים כל ימי חייך. Shene'emar
lema'an tizkor es yom tzeischa me'eretz Mitzrayim kol yemei chayecha. You have
to remember the Exodus all of the days of your life. כל
ימי חייך ימים. Kol yemei chayecha yamim. The days of your life
is daytime. כל ימי חייך הלילות. Kol yemei chayecha haleilos. All of
the days meaning the fullness of the day, not just daytime but
the full day, day and night. So that is הלילות. haleilos. וחכמים
אומרים ימי חייך העולם הזה. Vachachamim omrim yemei chayecha haolam hazeh. No,
more literal, more sense of like the number of days, not the
fullness of each day. So the days of your life is the
days of this life. כל כל ימי חייך. Kol kol yemei chayecha.
All the days of your life doesn't mean twice a day, but
it means even you'll always be saying it להביא לימות המשיח. Lehavi
limos Hamashiach. Even in the time of משיח Mashiach when there will
be a greater
salvation. Nevertheless, we will still always remember the paradigm and the original
גאולה geulah redemption of יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. תניא. Tanya. אמר להם בן זומא לחכמים. Amar
lahem Ben Zoma lachachamim. בן זומא Ben Zoma said to the
sages: וכי מזכירין יציאת מצרים לימות המשיח? Vechi mazkirin Yetzias Mitzrayim limos
Hamashiach? You would really think we should be doing that, or you
would do that at the time of משיח? Mashiach? והלא כבר נאמר
הנה ימים באים נאום השם ולא יאמרו עוד חי השם אשר העלה
את בני ישראל מארץ מצרים. Vhalo kvar ne'emar hinei yamim ba'im neum
Hashem vilo yomru od chai Hashem asher he'ela es benei Yisrael me'eretz
Mitzrayim. Days will be coming, no longer will you say by the
life of God who took the בני ישראל benei Yisrael out of
Egypt. כי אם חי השם אשר העלה ואשר הביא את זרע בית
ישראל מארץ צפונה ומכל הארצות אשר הדחתים שם. Ki im chai Hashem
asher he'ela va'asher hevi es zera beis Yisrael me'eretz tzafona umikol ha'aratzos
asher hidachtim sham. You will take an oath in the name of
God who has taken us from all of the exiles and from
בבל Bavel and brought us back at the time of the ultimate
redemption. So that will be the focus, the ultimate redemption, no longer
יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. So we will no longer mention it. אמרו
לו. Amru lo. They said back to him: לא שתעקר יציאת מצרים
ממקומה. Lo shetei'aker Yetzias Mitzrayim mimekoma. It doesn't mean that it loses
its
status. אלא שתהא שעבוד מלכויות עיקר ויציאת מצרים טפל לו. Ela sheteihei
shibud malchuyos ikar veYetzias Mitzrayim tafel lo. That the focus will be
at that point on having been freed from the subjugation of all
the other nations and having achieved the ultimate redemption. But it doesn't
mean that יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim loses its status. That still will
have its status, we'll still remember it, it will still always have
been the original act of redemption that was the sort of, if
you would, the source of all future redemptions. כיוצא בו אתה אומר.
Kayozei bo ata omer. Similarly, the idea of when something comes in
addition but not to supplant the earlier thing. It says: לא יקרא
שמך עוד יעקב כי אם ישראל יהיה שמך. Lo yikarei shimcha od
Yaakov ki im Yisrael yiheyeh shemecha. Your name will no longer be
יעקב Yaakov but rather it will be ישראל. Yisrael. So we know
that he was still called יעקב Yaakov after that. לא שיעקר יעקב
ממקומו. Lo sheye'aker Yaakov mimekomo. Not that his name יעקב Yaakov will
be uprooted, because God called him יעקב Yaakov after that. אלא ישראל
עיקר ויעקב טפל לו. Ela Yisrael ikar veYaakov tafel lo. The basic
name from now on will be ישראל, Yisrael, but יעקב Yaakov will
still be one of your names. וכן הוא אומר אל תזכרו ראשונות
וקדמוניות אל תתבוננו. Vechen hu omer al tizkru rishonos vekadmoniyos al tisbonanu.
Do not remember the early ones and the first ones and the
early ones, do not sort of contemplate. אל תזכרו ראשונות זו שעבוד
מלכויות. Al tizkru rishonos zu shibud malchuyos. וקדמוניות אל תתבוננו זו יציאת
מצרים. Vekadmoniyos al tisbonanu zu Yetzias Mitzrayim. So this you know so
both
you won't meaning you won't remember the servitude of the first ones
and of the קדמוניות. kadmoniyos. So both the שעבוד מלכויות, shibud malchuyos,
I don't know why it's called ראשונות, rishonos, but anyway, and of
you know so you'll remember the exile as it were both of
the early ones of the מלכויות malchuyos and also of יציאת מצרים,
Yetzias Mitzrayim, so you will always remember both. הנני עושה חדשה עתה
תצמח. Hinni oseh chadasha ata titzmach. I will now do a new
thing, now the salvation will rise up. And therefore you will no
longer be mired in the שעבוד shibud of the. mired in the
שיעבוד shibbud of the past. תני רב יוסף Tani Rav Yosef זו
מלחמת גוג ומגוג. zu milchemes Gog uMagog. This is the war of
גוג ומגוג. Gog uMagog. משל למה הדבר דומה לאדם שהיה מהלך בדרך
ופגע בו זאב. Mashal lema hadavar domeh leadam shehayah mehalech baderech upaga
bo zeev. A person was going on the way and he encountered
a wolf. וניצל הימנו, venitzal heimenu, he was saved from it. והיה
מספר והולך מעשה זאב, vehaya mesaper veholech maaseh zeev, he would tell
everybody who would listen about this amazing miracle that he was saved
from the wolf. ופגע בו ארי, upaga bo ari, then the next
time he encountered a lion. וניצל הימנו, venitzal heimenu, he was saved
from it. והיה מספר והולך מעשה ארי, vehaya mesaper veholech maaseh ari,
then he told everybody about the lion. Oh my God, this was
so amazing, I was saved from a lion. ופגע בו נחש, upaga
bo nachash, then he encountered a snake, presumably it's more dangerous than
a lion. וניצל הימנו. venitzal heimenu. שכח מעשה שניהם. shachach maaseh sheneihem.
He forgot about both. והיה מספר והולך מעשה נחש. vehaya mesaper veholech
maaseh nachash. So and he would go ahead and he would talk
about the about the snake and not about the earlier ones. אף
כך ישראל צרות אחרונות משכחות את הראשונות. Af kach Yisrael tzaros achronos
meshakchos es harishonos.
Similarly for the Jewish people, the later ones make us, you know,
ברוך השם Baruch Hashem or whatever are so you know have sort
of like the Gemara before about דיה לצרה בשעתה, daya litzara besha'ata,
you know we
we have one series of afflictions after the next. So when we
have the new one it seems you know even bigger than the
last one and we forgot the last one and we just focus
on the new one. Now I have to tell you that the
theme here
in this משל, mashal, right, is saying that it's משכחות, meshakchos, the
others...
I know, I know. So I agree. So it's a little funny
way to end because if anything this seems to, you know, to
more support the opinion that says that we won't be saying in
the future about יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim because we'll have forgotten it
because of, you know, because of the the extent of the how,
you know, because our current suffering and affliction is that much greater
and that overwhelms. So I really, you know, I really don't have
an answer except if the גמרא's Gemara point is that's why we
have to continue to remember, because since human nature is to focus
on only the most recent
and therefore, you know, דווקא davka the מצווה mitzvah is to not
forget even the earlier ones because the earlier ones were also miracles
and we can't just, you know, even though the inclination is that
the last one is the greatest miracle perhaps and the one we'll
certainly subjectively remember the most but you know maybe דווקא davka that's
why we're told that we have to continue to remember the earlier
ones. But you're right, it's a little funny. The גמרא Gemara doesn't
exactly sort of close the circle. Let's finish till the end of
the פרק. perek. Okay, since we're talking about supplanting versus not supplanting
let's take a look. אברם הוא אברהם. Avram hu Avraham. So this
is from דברי הימים. Divrei Hayamim. It says אברם Avram is אברהם.
Avraham. בתחילה נעשה אב לארם, Betichila naaseh av leAram, first he was
אברם Avram like אב av just for ארם, Aram, the people of
his nation which was ארם נהרים, Aram Naharayim, ובסוף נעשה אב לכל
העולם כולו. Ubesof naaseh av lechol haolam kulo. The ה hei meant
אב av for you know for the entire world. אב המון גוים.
Av hamon goyim. So somehow the אברהם Avraham המון, hamon, the father
of many nations.
שרי היא שרה, Sarai hi Sarah, also from דברי הימים. Divrei Hayamim.
שרי Sarai is שרה. Sarah. בתחילה נעשית שרי לאומתה Betichila naasis Sarai
leumasa
ובסוף נעשית שרה לכל העולם כולו. Ubesof naasis Sarah lechol haolam kulo.
So originally she was שרי Sarai like individual, my master, so for
her nation and in the end she would be שרה Sarah without
any possessive, the master for all people. תני בר קפרא כל הקורא
לאברהם אברם עובר בעשה. Tani Bar Kappara kol hakoreh leAvraham Avram over
beaseh. So where יעקב Yaakov the name did not supplant, by אברהם
Avraham the name did supplant. And anybody who calls אברהם Avraham אברם
Avram actually transgresses a positive מצווה mitzvah שנאמר shene'emar והיה שמך אברהם.
vehaya shimcha Avraham. Your name shall be אברהם. Avraham. רבי אליעזר אומר
עובר בלאו. Rabbi Eliezer omer over belav. Not only that if you
do it you're transgressing a negative prohibition שנאמר shene'emar ולא יקרא עוד
את שמך אברם. velo yikarei od es shimcha Avram. You shall no
longer, not just meaning a declaration of fact people won't call it
but it's actually a prohibition. People shall not call you anymore אברם.
Avram. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה הקורא לשרה שרי הכי
נמי. ella me'ata hakoreh leSarah Sarai hachi nami. So maybe the same
would be true about שרה Sarah and שרי. Sarai. So maybe we
should say it. So גמרא Gemara says no. התם קודשא בריך הוא
אמר לאברהם שרי אשתך לא תקרא את שמה שרי כי שרה שמה.
Hasam Kudsha Brich Hu amar leAvraham Sarai ishtecha lo tikra es shema
Sarai ki Sarah shema. That God said to אברהם Avraham Sarai your
wife
her name shall not be called שרי Sarai rather שרה שמה. Sarah
shema.
So right, so
one minute...
He should not call her, not anyone else.
Right, I know, לא תקרא lo tikra but it's not
even right, right, that's important, right. It's in the second person. It's
not
לא יקרא lo yikarei about other you know shall not be called
which is to everybody but לא תקרא lo tikra you know אתה
לא תקרא ata lo tikra you shall not call her name but
it's not to everybody. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה הקורא
ליעקב יעקב הכי נמי. ella me'ata hakoreh leYaakov Yaakov hachi nami. So
maybe by יעקב Yaakov also says right it says what's the פסוק
pasuk
לא יקרא שמך עוד יעקב. lo yikarei shimcha od Yaakov. So what?
So the גמרא Gemara says שאני התם. shani hasam. No there it's
different. דהדר אהדריה קרא דכתיב ויאמר אלהים לישראל. dehadar ahadrei kra dechtiv
vayomer Elokim leYisrael. ויאמר אלקים לישראל במראות הלילה ויאמר יעקב יעקב. Vayomer
Elokim leYisrael bemarei halaylah vayomer Yaakov Yaakov. So God did it. So
we know there it doesn't really mean—it doesn't mean it cannot be
at all, there it means it should not be the focus, it
should not be the primary. But by אברהם Avraham we say that
it's actually fully prohibited and by שרה Sarah only not because God
was talking only to אברהם Avraham and not generally. And then the
גמרא Gemara says מתיבי Mativei רב יוסף בר חבין Rav Yosef bar
Chavin ואי תימא ve'isayma רב יוסף בר זביד Rav Yosef bar Zevid
אתה הוא ה׳ אלקים אשר בחרת באברם. Atah hu Hashem Elokim asher
bacharta beAvram.
You God chose אברם, Avram, so there the פסוק pasuk did not
say
אברהם. Avraham. פאמר ליה Pa'amar lei התם נביא הוא דקא מסדר לשבחיה
דרחמנא Hatam navi hu deka mesadeir lishvachei deRachmana מה דהוה מעיקרא. mah
dehavei me'ikara. There the נביא navi is praising about the past. You
had chosen him when he was אברם Avram and you now they
gave him the name אברהם. Avraham.
So, so, but you're not actually now referring to him as אברהם.
Avraham. Now the question becomes and somebody actually asked me this question
and I've also wondered this. So let's say you're giving a—you're talking
about, you're giving a שיעור shiur on פרשת לך לך. Parshas Lech
Lecha. Can you say when God said to אברם Avram לך לך
מארצך, Lech lecha me'artzecha, right? Or do you have to say when
God said to אברהם? Avraham? Now most of us anyway would say
when God said to אברהם. Avraham. But would you be עובר oveir
on this? Would this be like the last line of the גמרא
Gemara that you're just talking about at that time that was his
name? Or not? Since you're saying when God there it's in the
context, you chose him as he was אברם Avram and you chose
him and gave him the name אברהם. Avraham. But when you're actually
talking about what he did you have to use his new name.
You can't be using his old name even if you're talking about
what he did when he had the old name or not. So
I don't know it's a little ambiguous. I מחמיר machmir about it,
not like I have too much of a יצר הרע. yetzer hara.
Normally we would anyway just call him אברהם. Avraham. But but you
know anyway it is interesting in terms of what exactly are those
parameters. Obviously to say you're really עובר oveir לאו, lav, really עובר
oveir עשה, asei, most assume that's a little bit of an אסמכתא.
asmachta. We're not saying it's a real biblical thing but nevertheless the
גמרא Gemara treats it seriously so it does raise those interesting questions.
Okay so we will end with this for now, nice ending of
that both mixed of both הלכה halacha and אגדתא agadata around the
ברכות berachot around שמע Shema and we will pick up with the
beginning of the second פרק perek tomorrow morning. Okay כל טוב kol
tuv everybody לילה טוב. layla tov.